Guide to the Julie Saul Gallery Records MSS.630
Fales Library and Special Collections
Julie Saul Gallery Records
1976-2021
Fales Library and Special Collections
Saul, Julie
Saul-Sena, Linda
MSS.630
13.50 Linear Feet in 31 manuscript boxes and 1 folder in a shared oversize flat box
The Julie Saul Gallery Records (1976-2021) document a woman-owned New York City art gallery active during the late 1980s to 2019 that specialized in traditional and avant-garde contemporary photography. This collection documents the Gallery's support, promotion, and exhibition of artists working in photography through artists payment receipts, exhibition planning files, press clippings, floor plans, and sales and consignment records. These records illustrate the administration of a gallery as well as the trends in art and artists through multiple decades. Additionally, Saul's journals document her business and personal travels in the United States, Canada, Europe, and Asia.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Linda Saul-Sena in June 2023; the accession number with this gift is 2023.039
Appraisal
The following were removed from the collection: 3 CDs (1 system disk and 2 data disks with duplicate images), invoices containing customer payment information, and duplicates of print material.
Arrangement
Material is arranged chronologically, with files grouped by subject.
Biographical Note
Julie Saul (1954-2022) was an American gallerist. She was educated as an art historian and curator. In the early 1980s she and Nancy Lieberman decided to establish a gallery to promote and sell photography. Saul eventually broke off with her own gallery in the 1990s and was known as a major exhibitor and supporter of traditional and avant-garde contemporary photography. In addition to the Gallery, Saul taught history of photography classes and also worked for 20 years on a project to promote the life and legacy of Berthe Weill, an early-20th-century Parisian art dealer.
(Source: New York Times Obituary, viewed 2/14/2022)
Historical Note
The Julie Saul Gallery initially began as Lieberman & Saul Fine Arts in 1984 where Saul and Nancy Lieberman worked as private dealers specializing in contemporary photographic-based art and works on paper. In 1986 they opened their first public space at 155 Spring Street and moved to 560 Broadway where Saul eventually transitioned the gallery to the Julie Saul Gallery in 1990. The Gallery began accumulating a balance of works on paper, collage, sculpture, painting, and video. Their location changed again, moving to 535 West 22nd Street in Chelsea, an area that many SoHo galleries were moving to in the mid-1990s. In addition to solo exhibitions for artists, the Gallery also curated an average of two thematic shows per year, often incorporating an historical component. Examples of these shows include Synapse Between Photography and Sculpture (1992), Richard Artschwager: Photo/Works 1945/1996,and Skin/Deep: A survey of interior imaging from X-Ray to MRI (1999). Artists represented included photographers Sally Gall, Andrew Bush, and Arne Svenson, as well as multimedia artists Richard Artschwager, Sarah Anne Johnson, and Maira Kalman. Saul closed the Gallery in 2019 when she lost her lease.
Scope and Contents
The Julie Saul Gallery Records document a New York City art gallery active during the late 1980s to 2019 that specialized in photography. This collection includes files accumulated by the Gallery on artists they represented including Richard Artschwager, Reinier Gerritsen, Bill Jacobson, Sara Anne Johnson, and Tseng Kwong Chi. Artist files often include press clippings, correspondence, resumes, artwork images, exhibition information, notes, and lists of the artworks and their prices. The collection also contains both chronological and individual Gallery exhibition files. These files typically contain promotional material, press releases, catalogs, correspondence, press clippings, notes, and artists' statements and resumes. Exhibition files containing a significant amount of material include Sally Gall -- Subterranea; Skin/Deep; Uncharted Territory; and Wordplay.
Gallery sales and consignment records range in date from the 1990s to the 2010s, documenting transactions between the gallery owner and purchasers, including other galleries, museums, and private collectors. These records track artwork pricing; the ebb and flow in popularity of artists and their works; and art mediums. The Gallery's payment receipts for individual artists illustrate the gallery/artist relationship in terms of profit-sharing, volume of purchases, and price tracking on individual artists. This collection also contains a small amount of documentation on the establishment of the original gallery with Nancy Lieberman in the 1980s; files accumulated on individual collectors; bills and expense lists; and press clippings regarding Julie Saul's early career and the Gallery.
Notes and copies of readings for photography art classes Saul attended in the 1980s are in this collection, as are notes and syllabi for classes she later taught on the subject. Julie Saul's travel journals date from 2002 to 2016, and include business and personal diary-type entries while visiting various parts of the United States, Canada, Europe, and Asia. These diaries also contain business contact information and meeting notes. There are also files related to Saul's outside projects during the 2000s-2010s including a Printed Matter portfolio project; research on French art dealer Berthe Weill; and The Color Project in which she partnered with Eileen Cohen.
Art galleries, Commerical -- New York (State) -- New York; business records; Art -- Exhibitions -- 20th century; Art -- Exhibitions -- 21st century.; Art -- Exhibitions -- New York (N.Y.); Photography, Artistic; Artists. -- New York (State) -- New York. -- 20th century; Artists -- United States -- 20th century; Receipts (financial records).; Exhibition Announcements.; Saul-Sena, Linda; Julie Saul Gallery; Artschwager, Richard, 1923-2013; Bartlett, Morton, 1909-1992; Martínez-Cañas, María; Tseng, Kwong Chi; Johnson, Sarah Anne, 1976-; Kalman, Maira; Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963; Massard, Didier; Bordwin, Andrew, 1964-; Gall, Sally, 1956-; Jacobson, Bill
- Publicity and Press Clippings -- Julie Saul and Gallery, 1976-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Photography Class Notes, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Correspondence, 1983-2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Artwork and Installation Images, circa 1980-2010s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Artist Files -- Artschwager, Richard, 1996-2015 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Artist Files -- Bakharev, Nikolay, 2001-2016 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Artist Files -- Bartlett, Morton, 1993-2015 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Artist Files -- Bellocq, E.J., 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Artist Files -- Berman, Zeke, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Artist Files -- Breakey, Kate, 1997-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Artist Files -- Bush, Andrew, 1986-2016 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Artist Files -- Campos-Pons, Maria Magdalena, 2001-2009 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Artist Files -- Cocteau, Jean, 1988-2005 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
- Artist Files -- Cohen, Elaine Lustig, 2007-2015 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Artist Files -- Cole, Ernest, circa 1990s-2018 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Artist Files -- Crosby, Suzanne Camp, 1985-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Artist Files -- Davis, Tim, 1999-2007 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Artist Files -- Dijkstra, Rineke, 1996-2007 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Artist Files -- Ellis, Darrel, 1996-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Artist Files -- Gall, Sally, 1985-2019 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
- Artist Files -- Gerritsen, Reinier, 2011-2014 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Artist Files -- Ghirri, Luigi, 1999-2002 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Artist Files -- Henri, Florence, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Artist Files -- Horna, Kati, circa 1985-2019 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Artist Files -- Hughes, Simon, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Artist Files -- Jacobson, Bill, 1991-2019 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Artist Files -- Johnson, Sarah Anne, 2005-2016 (Box 5, Folder 5-8, Box 6, Folder 1, Box Shared Fales 109)
- Artist Files -- Kalman, Maira, 2003-2021 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
- Artist Files -- Kim, Soo, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Artist Files -- Kremer, Shai, 2007-2010 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Artist Files -- Leist, Reiner, 2006-2008 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Artist Files -- Liao, Jeff Chien-Hsing, 2006-2012 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Artist Files -- Logan, Zachari, 2015-2020 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Artist Files -- Lund, Birgitta, 2006-2007 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Artist Files -- Lynes, George Platt, 1989-1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Artist Files -- Madahar, Neeta, 2005-2011 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Artist Files -- Magyar, Adam, 2014-2016 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Artist Files -- Marcuse, Tanya, 2008-2017 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Artist Files -- Martínez-Cañas, María, 1992-2018 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
- Artist Files -- Massard, Didier, 1998-2015 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
- Artist Files -- Müller, Karin Apollonia, 2000-2005 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Artist Files -- Pepperstein, Pavel, 2012-2017 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Artist Files -- Puch, Gonzalo, 2007-2011 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Artist Files -- Raff, Orit, 2005-2008 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Artist Files -- Russell, Christopher, 2001-2016 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Artist Files -- Sahlman, Jack, 1992, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Artist Files -- Schackwitz, Michael, 1983-1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Artist Files -- Schneider, Gary, 1988-2006 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Artist Files -- Shambroom, Paul, 1998-2002 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Artist Files -- Smith, Debra, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Artist Files -- Stoetzel, Lee, 1996-2004 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Artist Files -- Svenson, Arne, 1997-2016 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Artist Files -- Tseng, Kwong Chi, 1984-2015 (Box 9, Folder 8, Box 10, Folder 1-7, Box 11, Folder 1-2)
- Artist Files -- van Balen, Céline, 1999-2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Artist Files -- van de Puttelaar, Carla, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Gallery Business Documentation and History, 1984-1995 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Collector File -- Goldfrank, 1986-1990 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Exhibition Files -- Chronological, 1986-1999 (Box 11, Folder 7-8, Box 12, Folder 1-5)
- Exhibition Files -- Chronological, 1999-2018 (Box 13, Folder 1-5, Box 14, Box 15, Folder 1-3)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Interiors, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Constructing Images, 1991-1992 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Lydia Schouten: Celebrating my 40th Birthday Alone at the Blue Hotel Room, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Shooting the Moon, 1995-1996 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Etude D'Apres Nature, 1996-1997 (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Adolescents, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Skin/Deep, 1998-1999 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Thin Air, 1999 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Into the Woods, 2002 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Mexico Exhibit, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Sally Gall -- Subterranea, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Uncharted Territory, 2004 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Alison Jackson, 2004 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Elements of Style -- Maira Kalman, circa 2004 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Wordplay, 2005 (Box 16, Folder 10-11)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Summer Show, 2005 (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Infected Landscape, 2006 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- When Color Was New, 2008 (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Charlotte Dumas, 2010 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Out of Nowhere, 2012 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- The Fold, 2015 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- Visions of Place, 2016 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Exhibition Files by Title -- 19 Years at 535, 2019 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Survey of Photographs Representing Marine Vessels -- Documentation, 1988-1993 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Artschwager, Richard, 1996-2018 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Baden, Karl, 2013 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Bakharev, Nikolay, 2012-2019 (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Bartlett, Morton, 2015-2016 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Berman, Zeke, 2016 (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Bordwin, Andrew, 1993-2016 (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Bush, Andrew, 1992-2018 (Box 18, Folder 7-8)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Campos-Pons, Maria Magdalena, 2007-2010 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Chun, Jesse, 2015-2016 (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Cole, Ernest, 2015 (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Dumas, Charlotte, 2011-2018 (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Fieret, Gerard, 2012-2013 (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Gall, Sally, 1989-2019 (Box 19, Folder 6-8)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Gerritsen, Reinier, 2002-2016 (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Ghirri, Luigi, 1998-2004 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Grossman, Debbie, 2011-2014 (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Grützner, Andrea, 2016-2019 (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Jacobson, Bill, 1994-2018 (Box 20, Folder 4-6)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Janssen, Carolyn, 2013 (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Johnson, Sarah Anne, 2002-2019 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Johnstone, Charles, 2013-2016 (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Kalman, Maira, 2002-2019 (Box 21, Folder 4-6)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Kremer, Shai, 2007-2018 (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Laviada, Alejandra, 2012-2018 (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Logan, Zachari, 2002-2019 (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Madahar, Neeta, 2005-2015 (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Magyar, Adam, 2014-2019 (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Marcuse, Tanya, 2007-2019 (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Martinez-Cañas, Maria, 1999-2018 (Box 23, Folder 6)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Massard, Didier, 1999-2019 (Box 23, Folder 7-8)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Müller, Karin Apollonia, 2001-2015 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Nelson, Catherine, 2013-2019 (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Pepperstein, Pavel, 2016-2017 (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Puch, Gonzalo, 2012-2017 (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Raff, Orit, 2000-2017 (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Reyes, Justine, 2012-2018 (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Russell, Christopher, 2002-2019 (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Samoylova, Anastasia, 2018 (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Sells, Chloe, 2014-2018 (Box 24, Folder 9)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Stephenson, David, 1996-2019 (Box 24, Folder 10-11)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Stewart, Iain, 1997-2015 (Box 24, Folder 12)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Svenson, Arne, 2000-2019 (Box 24, Folder 13)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Tseng, Kwong Chi, 1996-2003 (Box 22, Folder 1-3)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Ulrich, Brian, 2006-2014 (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Artist Payment Receipts -- Whetstone, Jeff, 2008-2019 (Box 22, Folder 5)
- Purchase Receipts, Collector -- Allaire, 1987-1989 (Box 22, Folder 6)
- Purchase Receipts, Collector -- Jack Sahlman, 1987-1993 (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Classes Taught by Julie Saul -- Course Material, Notes, Syllabi, 1990-2000 (Box 22, Folder 8-9)
- Artwork Invoices -- Purchased by Gallery, 1990-2016 (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
- Artwork Sales Ledger, 1990-1998 (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Artwork Sales Invoices, 2008-2013 (Box 25, Folder 4-5, Box 26, Folder 1-5)
- Artwork Sales Invoices, 2013-2019 (Box 27, Folder 1-5, Box 28)
- Appointment Book, 1991 (Box 28, Folder 6)
- Germany Trip Planning, 1992 (Box 28, Folder 7)
- French Portrait Collection Project -- Artwork Lists, Prices, Articles, 1992-1997, 2008 (Box 29, Folder 1)
- Gallery Inventory Price Lists, 1994-1999 (Box 29, Folder 2)
- Gramercy Art Fair -- Notes, 1996 (Box 29, Folder 3)
- Jack Sahlman Photographic Collection -- Appraisal and Related, 1997 (Box 29, Folder 4)
- Gallery Bills and Expenses, 1997-2001 (Box 29, Folder 5)
- Auction Purchases by Gallery -- Invoices, 1997-2014 (Box 29, Folder 6)
- Gallery History Statement, circa 1999 (Box 29, Folder 7)
- Consignment Agreements with Other Galleries, 2000-2001 (Box 29, Folder 8)
- Basel-Venice Trip Planning, 2001 (Box 29, Folder 9)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- London and Berlin, 2002 (Box 29, Folder 10)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- India and France, 2004 (Box 29, Folder 11)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- Spain, 2005 (Box 30, Folder 1)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- Netherlands, Italy, Hungary, Austria, 2006-2007, 2009 (Box 30, Folder 2)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- Paris, Los Angeles, London, 2007, 2010, 2016 (Box 30, Folder 3)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- California, Canada, France, Florida, 2010 (Box 30, Folder 4)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- Paris, Rome, 2012 (Box 30, Folder 5)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- London, Italy, Amsterdam, Canada, 2012-2013 (Box 30, Folder 6)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- Icelands, Russia, France, India, 2014-2015 (Box 30, Folder 7)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- Los Angeles and Venice, Paris, San Francisco, 2015-2016 (Box 30, Folder 8)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- Mexico, Marfa, London, Cornwall, 2016, 2018 (Box 31, Folder 1)
- Notebooks/Travel Diaries -- India, December, Undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
- Julie Saul's Art Collection -- Articles, Note, 2003-2016 (Box 31, Folder 3)
- The Color Project with Julie Saul and Eileen Cohen -- Agreement, Notes, Correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 31, Folder 4)
- Printed Matter Portfolio Project -- Notes, Lists, 2008-2009 (Box 31, Folder 5)
- Sold Artworks Inventory, 2009-2015 (Box 31, Folder 6)
- Julie Saul Gallery Booth Proposal for Art Dealers Association of America (ADAA), 2016 (Box 31, Folder 7)
- Berthe Weill Project -- Notes, Research, 2016 (Box 31, Folder 8-9)
- László Moholy-Nagy and Irene-Charlotte Lusk Project Notes, Undated (Box 31, Folder 10)